Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 13 -- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials 1640-1791 Mss.B.F85inventory13
American Philosophical Society
- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials
  - to Jonathan Williams, [Jr.]., 1777 August 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Wickes, Lambert. St. Malo
    Acknowledging his favor of the 17th. Refers him to a Resolve of Congress which says that a man who deserts a vessel has no right to claim pay or a share of the prize money; however will do what Dr. Franklin thinks necessary. Sorry to hear his character is so bad in France.
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1777 August 25; Printed D.S. 1p.; P.M. Porquet and Quentin Caffieri. Calais
    Order given to Jean Merry, Captain of a French corsair, who had been a prisoner in England, to report to the French naval authorities.
  - to Abbé Le Clerc [de St. Etvain], Paris., 1777 September 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Sutton, A.B.Paris
    Begging him to obtain for him from Messrs. Franklin and Deane a letter of marque. His zeal for the cause of the colonies.
  - to Silas Deane, Passy., 1777 September 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Lee, William. Nantes
    Relative to business transactions with M. Penet who refuses to make settlement.
  - Miscellaneous Paper, 1777 September 8; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 2p.; The Continental Congress
    Report of the Committee of Foreign Applications and the action on the same.
    (In triplicate.)
    Printed in the Journals of the Continental Congress, Philadelphia [1778], III, 77.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 September 8, 13, 14; October 4, 10, 13; November 15, 17; D. 4p.; The Continental Congress
    Resolutions of Congress in relation to foreign officers.
    Printed in the Journals of Congress, Philadelphia [1778], III, 377, 391, 392, 406, 425, 430, 512, 513.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 September 10; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    In respect to payment of Loan Office Certificates.
    Printed in the Journals of Continental Congress, Philadelphia [1778], III, 385.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 September 14 and October 17; A.D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    In reference to drawing bills of exchange.
    Printed in the Journals of the Continental Congress, Philadelphia [1778], III, 392, 439.
  - to General [Benjamin] Lincoln., 1777 September 18; L.S. 3p.; Brown, John. North End of Lake George Landing New York
    An account of the capture of that place. Mount Defiance and the old French lines at Ticonderoga also fell into his hands. Has sent a flag demanding the surrender of Ty and Mount Independence. Has had as yet no information of Col. Johnson's attack on the Mount. Has a small quantity of provisions which will necessitate his retreat in case Ty and Mount Independence are not carried. Hopes he will give him assistance in crossing the Lake should be need it. The enemy at Fort George. Just received General Powel's answer to his demands saying he shall defend the garrison, entrusted to his charge, to the last. Has little hope of putting him to the necessity of giving it up unless by the force under Col. Johnson.
  - to Major General Gates., 1777 September 20; L.S. 2p.; Lincoln, Gen. Benjamin. Castleton Vt
    Concurs in his opinion that as soon as their views are accomplished it will be best to remove near him, either on the flank or in the rear of General Burgoyne. Waits with great impatience the issue of their expedition to Ticonderoga. General Warren went to Mount Independence to take charge of the troops before that place. Leaves the farther conducting of matters this way with him and General Jacob Bayley. He collects the remainder of his troops in his division and moves downward.
  - to John Hancock., 1777 September 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Gates, Gen. Horatio. Camp. Heights above Behmus's Bemis's N. Y
    Was informed that the enemy had struck their camp and were moving on his left, detached Col. [Daniel] Morgan's corps to observe their direction and to harass their advance. An account of the skirmishes that ensued and the battle that followed. Results of the conflict Bravery of the American soldiers. Wrote to all the neighboring States and pressingly demanded the immediate march of their militia.
  - to John Hancock., 1777 September 22; L.S. 2p.; Gates, Gen. Horatio. Camp. Heights above Behmus's Bernis's, N. Y
    The letters he received from General [Benjamin] Lincoln and Col [John] Brown and congratulates him and the Congress on the remarkable success of the armies of the United States. Thinks there is now a fair prospect of the Northern States soon being freed from the enemies who threatened no less than the conquest of the entire State.
  - to Marquis de Luce-Seillans., 1777 September 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Can make arrangements to land him at any city in America.
  - to John Hancock, President of Congress., 1777 October 5; L.S. 3p.; Washington, Gen. George. Camp at Pennibacker's Mill
    Received the intelligence by two intercepted letters, that General Howe had detached a part of his force for the purpose of reducing Billingsport and the Forts on the Delaware. Resolved, with the other Generals, to attack the English at or near Germantown. The plan of attack. The attack and its results.
  - to A Member of Congress., 1777 October 5; L. 1p.; Washington, Gen. George
    In regard to the battle of Germantown and the causes which hindered it from being a success.
  - to ------- -------., 1777 October 10; L. 3p.; A Member of Congress. Yorktown
    In regard to the cause of the retreat of the American forces at the battle of Germantown and the results of the battle in killed and wounded. Captain [John] Barry recaptured the [Pennsylvania] frigate "Delaware," recently captured by the English. The condition of the American forces.
  - to ----- Murphy [prisoner on His Majesty's ship "Æolus"]., 1777 October 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Yates, Thomas L. Admiral's House
    The Admiral informed by several of the principal people in trade here, that were he to be delivered up he would probably be executed on this Island, and, fearing his escape, he thought proper to keep him in irons until one of His Majesty's ships is sent to England.
  - to Gen. Burgoyne., 1777 October 11; L. 2p.; Gates, Gen. Horatio. Saratoga
    Acknowledging his Excellency's letter by lady Ackland; surprised that the General should consider the greatest attention to Lady A. in the light of an obligation. Cruelties practised by the English army during their retreat are without a precedent among civilized people. His Excellency's friend, Sir Francis Clark, languishes under a very dangerous wound, but is treated with every tenderness and attention. Offers Major Williams and Major Meiborn in exchange for Col. Ethan Allen.
    (Copy enclosed in letter of John Langdon of October 29, 1777, see Vol. I, p. 304.)
  - to Silas Deane, Paris., 1777 October 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Folger, John
    Is willing to undertake a certain secret mission.
  - to John Hancock., 1777 October 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Gates, Gen. Horatio. Camp of Saratoga
    Skirmishes that took place near Saratoga, and their results. Major Gen. [Benedict] Arnold's leg was fractured by a musket ball. A letter from [Gen. John] Burgoyne acquainting him that he left his whole hospital to his protection, in which are 300 wounded officers and soliders. The enemy retreated to the opposite side of the Fish Kill and burned everything before them. Desertion has taken deep root in the Royal Army, particularly among the Germans.
  - to ------ ------., 1777 October 4; XLVII, 84a.; "A General Officer". Pawlings's Mills
    Extract from a letter in regard to the plan and battle at Gemantown.
  - Miscellaneous PApers, 1777 October 18; A.D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Resolution in relation to the resolve of the House of Assembly of Georgia in reference to engaging officers belonging to foreign countries.
    Printed in the Journals of the Continental Congress, Philadelphia [1778], III, 445.
  - to The President of the Council of Massachusetts Bay., 1777 October 19; L.S. 2p.; Gates, Gen. Horatio. Albany
    Incloses a copy of a convention by which Lieutenant-General Burgoyne surrendered himself and his whole army. General [John] Glover and General [William] Whipple, with proper guard of militia, escort them to Boston. Is pushing his army forward to stop the cruel career of General [John] Vaughan up Hudson's River.
  - to Rawleigh Colston., 1777 October 20; L.S. 2p.; Henry, Patrick. Williamsburg, Va
    Appointed to act as Agent for Virginia in the Island of Hispaniola. His duties and the directions which he is to observe.
  - to The Board of War at Boston., 1777 October 26; D.S. 2p.; ----- and Cauvou and Chevalier De Franval. Boston
    Promises to pay Jonathan Loring Austin, for their account, passage money to Nantes or other port of France.
  - to William Carmichael., 1777 October 31; A.D.S. 3p.; Oliphant, J
    In regard to the purchase of vessels for the purpose of scouring the North Seas. Terms on which these vessels are being bought. Heard that an engagement had taken place between General Washington and General Howe, and that the former was defeated with heavy loss. Instructions to Letters of Marque. General Howe landed in Oak River.
  - to Mme. Duboccage., 1777 November 2; L. 2p.; Voltaire, François-Marie Arouet. Ferney
    Reply about his tragedy "Alzire." Says he is not a genius but an man of eighty-four weighed down with infirmities, half poet and of philosopher. Will soon rejoin his old masters, Socrates and Sophos. Compliments Mme. Duboccage. If he desired anything now, would be to return to Paris to enjoy her agreeable society. His niece has been very ill also.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 November 7; D. 4p.; The Continental Congress
    The Report of the Board of Treasury concerning the claims of M. le Brun and other Frenchmen who came to America in consequence of an agreement with Mr. [Silas] Deane, and the resolutions of the Continental Congress in connection therewith.
    Printed in the Journals of Congress, Philadelphia [1778], 111, 482.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 November 8.; Copy of D. 2p.; The Continental Congress
    Resolutions relative to a roster of General Burgoyne's army and General [William] Heath's order of November 20, 1777, in consequence thereof, with copy of his letter to Henry Laurens, dated Boston November 27, informing Congress of the action taken by him to carry out the resolution.
    Resolution printed in the Journals of Congress. Philadelphia [1778], 111, 481.
  - to ---------., 1777 November 11.; A.L.S 1p.; Wuybert, Antoine-Félix. Paris
    Still a prisoner. Claims the right to be included in the first exchange being a French officer of high rank, in the service of the United State. Would like his fellow prisoner, a French Lieutenant-Colonel of cavalry to be exchanged at same time; have to endure all kinds of hardship an privations. Requests him to confer with Messrs. Franklin and Dear about their release.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 November14.; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 3p.; The Continental Congress
    Resolutions concerning gratuities to the officer who accompanies Mons. Du Coudray from France.
    Printed in the Journals of Congress, Philadelphia [1778], 111, 498.
  - to General [Horatio] Gates., 1777 November 14; L.S. 2p.; Burgoyne Gen. John. Cambridge
    Account of the forces under his command on the day of signing the Convention. The British troops accomplished the march without any complaint on their part or against them. Complains of the miserable quarters given him and his officers. Alleges a breach of public faith.
  - to Silas Deane, paris., 1777 November 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Mackean, William. London
    Taken prisoner on the sloop "Catharine," bound from Bordeaux to Boston; brought to Portsmouth and kept there thirteen weeks upon suspicion; received his discharge, but is destitute; desires Franklin to assist him to return home; refers him to the bearer, M. Millin de la Brosse, who was one of his fellow sufferers.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 November 17; D. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Resolution giving commissions to Chevalier [Louis Le Bègue] Duportail, and Messierus de Laumoy, [Deshays] De la Radière and [Jean Baptiste de] Gouvion.
    Printed in the Journals of Congress, Philadelphia [1778], III, 513.
  - to General [William] Heath., 1777 November 20; D.S. 1p.; Burgoyne Gen. John. Cambridge
    Received a paper dated Headquarters, Boston, November 20, purporting to be founded upon the express from the Congress, which he returns as inadmissible because it extends to matters in which the Congress has no right to interfere. Before any lists are granted he must be assured of purpose for which they are intended and the word order must neither be mentioned or implied.
  - to General John Burgoyne., 1777 November 21; L.S. 2p.; Heath, Gen. William. Headquarters, Boston
    Informs him that the Continental Congress has a right in matters of the Convention. Wants to ascertain the number of officers and men comprehended in the Convention that in case any of them, contrary to their faith, should again bear arms against the Colonies in the present war they may be convicted of the offence. The other list necessary for the Quartermasters and Commissaries. Hopes they will be sent for the purposes mentioned without delay.
  - to General [William] Heath., 1777 November 23; L.S. 2p.; Burgoyne Gen. John. Cambridge
    Insists that Congress, as the executive power of the State, has no right to issue an order to persons not their subjects, on a matter no way relating to the civil government of the country. Defies him to find a single instance in the history of military conventions, when any security was demanded of the surrendered army not to serve for a limited time, other than the pledge of National faith. Looks upon the reasons given for demanding a descriptive list, as an insult to his country. Calls attention to the fact that Sir Guy Carleton and he released from Canada many hundred Continental prisoners, upon the bare parole of not serving against the King till exchanged.
  - to General [William] Heath., 1777 November 24; L.S. 1p.; Burgoyne Gen. John. Cambridge
    Received dispatch from Sir William Howe informing him that transports were preparing, with all possible expedition, to carry the troops under the Convention to England. Begs the favor of an interview as soon as possible, that he may settle the matter in regard to the embarkation, so as to prevent any delays. Also desires to discuss, and finally to settle, the several matters at present in agitation between them.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 November 28; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Appointing William Carmichael, Secretary to the Commissioners at the Court of France.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 November 28; Copy of D.S. 1p.; The House of Delegates of Maryland. Annapolis
    Resolution of the House of Delegates of Maryland to apply to the Courts of France and Spain for arms, ammunition, etc.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 December 2; Printed L.S. 1p.; Dubois and Thiérin. Paris
    Have formed a new banking firm under above name.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 December 3; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 2p.; The Continental Congress
    Resolutions respecting loans in Europe and their conditions.
    Printed in the Journals of Congress, Philadelphia [1778], III, 552.
  - to Jonathan Williams, [Jr.]., 1777 December 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Morris, Thomas. Nantes
    Finds it necessary to have an assistant in conducting the business committed on him by the Secret Committee; offer this position on certain terms to Mr. Williams.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 December 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Agreeable to his request, consents to take an active part in the business committed to Mr. Morrris's care by the Secret Committee of Congress.
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1777 December 11; D. 4p.; Agreement Between the Owners of the ship "La Brune" and the Crew. L'Orient
    For a voyage to America and return.
  - to President [Henry] Laurens., 1777 December 12; L. 1p.; Trumbull, Gov. Jonathan. Lebanon
    Expresses his opinion that the British troops ought not to be embarked at any other port but that stipulated in the Convention. Hears that the Governor and Council of Rhode Island sent a protest to Boston, against their march to and embarkation at Rhode Island. Incloses a copy of a letter from General [Robert] Pigot to General Burgoyne relative to the embarkation of Burgoyne's troops at Rhode Island.
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1777 December 19; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Resolutions in reference to the subsistence of prisoners.
    Printed in the Journals of Congress, Philadelphia [1778], III, 581.
  - to Silas Deane., 1777 December 19; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Gérard, Conrad Alexandre
    Requests him to send with his letter, a letter of credit for 15, 000 livres payable at place of destination.
  - to Thomas Morris, Nantes., 1777 December 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Willing, Morris and Co. Manheim in Pennsylvania
    Forbid him to draw, for balances due them, upon any of their friends in England or any part of Europe. Hope, that should he have drawn or received any money previous to the receipt of this letter, he employed it in making such payments as they have at various times directed him. Direct him to deliver such money as he may have in his hands to John Ross, of Philadelphia, now in Europe, who is the bearer of this letter. Request him to make up all account and to pay the balance, should there be one in their favor, to Mr. Ross. Inform him that as the copartnership in which he was concerned is dissolved, they must settle all accounts; promise to pay him anything that may be due him and desire him to be ready to pay them what may be due them.
  - to Henry Laurens, President of Congress., 1777 December 26; A.L.S. 7p.; Morris, Robert. Manheim, Pennsylvania
    Relative to the disgrace his brother brought upon him. An account of his brother's early life and the circumstances which induced him to recommend his brother to the agency in Europe. Accounts for his granting greater faith to his brother's presentation of his conduct that to the Commissioner's letters. Earnestly regrets what he has been guilty of and promises to make suitable acknowledgments to both Dr. Franklin and Mr. [Silas] Deane.
  - to Silas Deane, Paris., 1777 December 27; L.S. 5p.; Morris, Robert. Manheim, Pennsylvania
    Explanations in regard to his previous letters relative to the misconduct of his brother, Thomas Morris, and his resolve to disow him as a brother, friend, or connection of any kind.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1777 December 29; D.S. 3p.; Younglove, Moses. Albany
    Surgeon in Gen. [Nichloas] Herkimer's brigade. Deposition describing the inhuman treatment of prisoners by the English and Indian.
  - to Ferdinand Grand., c. 1777; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Germany, ----- de
    Dr. Franklin promised to send Professor [Horace Bénédict] de Saussure some information about the lightning rods used in America. Asks M. Grand to remind him of his promise.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Mem. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    List and particulars of cannon wanted by the United States, to be purchased in Holland.
  - to Comte de St. Germain, Minister of War., Mem. in 3d P. 2p.; Captain Stephano, Baron de Bissy
    Offers his invention of a cheval-de-frise for the protection of the infantry.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, [1777.]; Mem. 2p.; The Loan of Two Million Sterling
    Which the United States Congress has authorized its Commissioners to contract for, in Europe.
  - to M. D'Alibart., L. in 3d P. 1p.; -----, -----
    Begs his intercession with Dr. Franklin to obtain service in the American army.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 January 10; D.S. Augustin de Cavril 3p.; Conyngham, Gustavus. St. Sebastian
    Power of attorney given by the Captain of the privateer "Reprisal" to Bernard Dehez.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 January 8; D.S. Henry Laurens, President. 5p.; The Continental Congress
    Report concerning the Convention entered into by General Burgoyne, at Saratoga.
    Printed in the Journals of Congress, Philadelphia [1779], IV, 14.
  - to ----- -----., 1778 January 10; L. 2p.; Jenneux, -----
    Has seen M. [Barbeu] Dubourg this morning. Encloses a note (1 p.), from him. Wishes to arrange an interview with Dr. Franklin.
  - to Messrs. [Thomas] Morris and [William] Lee., 1778 January 10; A.L.S. 1p.; John Bradford, Continental Agent. Boston
    Requests them, on the delivery of the cargo on board the brig "Tryton," to pay Captain P[eter] Collas £80, being an allowance made him for his primage; also to pay him three shillings four pence, for his daily expenses.
  - to ------ Lampre., 1778 Januray 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Burnell, Capt. John. Mill Prison
    Asks to be supplied with £50 and begs him not to let anyone have the boat without an order from him.
  - to [Jean Baptiste] Le Roy., 1778 Janurary 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Burnell, Capt. John. Plymouth, Mill Prison
    Has received no answers to his letters to M. Dulonprey; has written for fifty pounds; desires him to be careful of the boat, brig and cargo.
  - to Silas Deane., 1778 January 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Saltonstall, Gurdon. Weathersfield, Vt
    Family news. Congratulations on the victory over Burgoyne; thinks it will produce from France a declaration of war against Great Britain. Expects General Washington to gain a victory over General Howe, before May next. Health and enthusiasm of the American troops remarkable. This letter is carried by Deane's son, Jesse.
  - to President [Henry] Laurens., 1778 January 31; L.S. 4p.; Caswell, Richard. North Carolina
    When he arrived at the place that Capt. [John] Folg(i)er mentioned, he showed him a package addressed to himself, which he claimed contained papers for Congress. Gov. Caswell found in the packet papers addressed to John Hancock, [Robert] Morris and other members of Congress. There were also several letters, endorsed "dispatches," which he did not open. Asserts that he again put all the letters and dispatches under the original cover and, after giving Folg(i)er the pass mentioned, sent him on, firmly persuaded that the papers to the President contained matters of an interesting nature to the States. Thinks if Folg(i)er has not delivered the packet he has certainly some design in secreting it, and hopes Congress may get such information as may enable them to do him justice.
    See Journals of Congress, Philadelphia [1779] IV, 21, 22, 273, 314.
  - to John Paul Jones., 1778 February 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Simpson, Thomas, Elijah Hall and David Cullman. "Ranger."
    They thought that Captain Matthew Parke, of the Marine Department, embarked on board the "Ranger" with a view of acting according to his rank in a frigate which he was to take the command of, on their arrival in France. Are informed that no Caption of Marines is allowed to any vessel under twenty guns. They take it as a hardship that a person in his capacity should remain in the ship to take the fourth part of the three-twentieths belonging to them, of any prize-money. Request him to dispose of Captain Parke in such a manner that he may not interfere with them in any future division.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 February 9; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Concerning the appointment of Commercial Agents.
    Printed in the Journals of Congress, Philadelphia [1779], IV, 82.
  - to Silas Deane., 1778 February 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. "Ranger."
    Encloses a letter for the Commissioners, and the latest newspapers.
  - to Silas Deane, Paris., 1778 February 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Nicholson, Samuel. Quiberon Bay